Antarctica in summer.
After months of darkness,
the sun has finally reappeared.
Ships can once again travel southwards.
They dare to venture into icy territory
only during the light season,
but winter's rigid, icy carapace
is not easy to penetrate.
Even for icebreakers,
voyages into South Polar Sea are risky.
Gigantic icebergs and stormy seas
are added dangers.
The coastal areas
around the subantarctic islands
are mostly ice-free,
serving as the habitat
for Antarctic's remarkably abundant fauna.
These narrow strips of land
serve as a fighting arena,
marriage market and breeding ground.
The Antarctic continent is enclosed
by a vast expanse of ice.
Emperor penguins have no problem
with the inhospitable conditions.
They're the largest penguin species.
The southernmost continent is their home,
their kingdom.
To us humans, it consists of tales,
tales of Antarctica,
from the End of the World.
The gateway to Antarctica
lies in the far south of Argentina,
Tierra del Fuego.
The sea is the best connection
to the rest of the world.
One of the few places that exist here
is renowned beyond the country's borders.
It's the resort town of Ushuaia,
also known as the End of the World.
Tapering off into the foothills
of the Andes Mountains
is the southern end
of the American continent.
Around 60,000 residents rely primarily
on fishing or tourism for sustenance.
The season begins in October
when visitors are lured
by the Southern Hemisphere summer.
Not far from the city,
it's breeding time
for Magellanic penguins.
Males and females share hatching duties,
going off in turns to find food.
Only occasionally can they indulge
in some time together.
Magellanic penguins live on fish,
squid and krill,
and there's a plentiful supply of these
in the cold waters of Tierra del Fuego.
Ushuaia is famous not only due to
the many cruise liners that stop here,
but particularly in its role
as the gateway to Antarctica.
It's the starting point
for numerous expeditions.
The Kapitan Khlebnikov is getting ready
for its next voyage into South Polar Sea.
Provisions are loaded,
and the last passengers board the vessel.
The best time to set out is the onset
of the local summer in November.
The lighthouse, Faro Les Éclaireurs, lies
around eight nautical miles from Ushuaia.
It marks the end of the habitable world
for human beings.
Animals, on the other hand,
are very much at home here,
as the waters are teeming
with sustenance for them.
South American sea lions will often choose
small, rocky islets as their retreat.
They rest and sleep here before embarking
on their next fishing foray.
The males don't have much downtime,
as they have to guard
and protect their harem.
The South American blackish oystercatcher
feeds on mussels,
which it cracks open with its hard beak.
The voyage of discovery goes from
the southern tip of the American continent
to the South Georgia Islands.
The Kapitan Khlebnikov is an icebreaker
with special technical equipment,
making it well-suited
for the passage to Antarctica.
A special radar system
sounds out the ice situation.
Its reinforced hull is designed
to break through sea ice
up to three meters thick.
Although the conditions
don't yet call for this capability,
the voyage is still not an easy one.
The erratic and often stormy weather here
has taught experienced seafarers
to have a healthy respect for the sea
at between 40 and 60 degrees latitude.
They've given it nicknames,
such as the Roaring 40s,
the Furious 50s,
and the Shrieking or Screaming 60s.
Gulls and other seabirds
accompany the ship,
defying the challenges of the wild sea.
South Georgia lies some
2,000 kilometers east of Tierra del Fuego,
part of the subantarctic islands.
Apart from a British governor
and two scientists,
the island is uninhabited.
Mountains, snow and ice
dominate the landscape.
At 2,934 meters,
Mount Paget is the highest peak.
All around the island,
more than 160 glaciers flow into the sea,
but the coast is ice-free
almost all year round.
Robust bull kelp, up to ten meters long,
grows in abundance here.
It's generally a safe environment
for fish, mussels and crabs,
except when the southern giant petrel
is hunting for food.
King penguins are the most
imposing residents of South Georgia.
They gather in the island's bays
in the Southern Hemisphere spring.
The males arrive first and look
for their breeding place from last year.
When they dive into the water,
they do it together in groups.
It's a reliable survival strategy
to escape predators lurking underwater.
King penguins are sociable
and like to hunt together.
Their prey is mainly fish and squid.
After about 150 daily dives,
they seek a resting place on the beach.
The narrow, ice-free beaches
between the glaciers and the sea
provide shelter from the wind and weather,
not only for penguins
but also for seals and other creatures.
A couple of weeks after the males,
the females follow
and begin to seek out their partner.
During the breeding season,
king penguins are strictly monogamous.
On land, adult penguins don't have
any natural predators in South Georgia,
but not all of them will return
from their long fishing trips in the sea.
Orcas and other predators take their toll.
Some penguins wait in vain
for their partner to return.
Their distinctive plumage shields them
from the cold and wetness.
The feathers atop
the underlying warm downy layer
must be preened and oiled regularly.
King penguins aren't
the only residents here.
In the summer,
the beaches of South Georgia
are positively bustling.
An elephant seal colony obstructs the path
from the breeding ground to the sea.
Only the adult males
sport the prominent eponymous trunk.
These giants can weigh up to four tons.
Young males don't have much
to show in the nose department yet.
It takes about eight years
for the olfactory organ to reach a size
where the wearer can make an impression.
They learn how to fight early on.
The young elephant seals
don't hold back either.
Strength, aggressiveness
and tactics are all decisive factors
in the fight for females and territory.
It's often a matter of life and death.
They have to start young.
Practice makes perfect.
His huge trunk and fighting ability
have earned him respect,
and he's got what he wanted.
The bull has gathered
15 females around him,
a respectable-sized harem.
They are mostly peaceable
and take care of their offspring.
This young fellow can still
only dream of future conquests.
It's good to relax,
surrounded by the family.
Wailing babies are part of it too.
The baby seal needs plenty of milk
and has to grow quickly.
There isn't much time for having fun.
Elephant seal pups must become
independent in just four weeks.
Life still seems carefree,
but in just a few weeks,
it will be time to start out
on their long ocean journey.
Till then, the seal pups quadruple
their birth weight to about 150 kilograms.
It's vital for them
to have a thick layer of fat
so they can survive
in the icy South Polar Sea.
Elephant seals only go ashore
during the mating season
to rear their young
and for their annual molt.
The remaining time is dedicated
to hunting fish and squid in the sea.
They spend months in the ocean
until their reproductive instinct
drives them to go ashore again.
South Georgia is a meeting point
for many animals who otherwise
spend their lives in the sea.
The craggy interior of the island
is dominated by glaciers, ice and snow,
not a good habitat for flora and fauna.
What sparse vegetation there is
can mostly be found
along the narrow coastal strip.
However, mosses thrive
in the subantarctic's damp, cold climate,
although temperatures in summer
rarely climb above ten degrees centigrade.
Countless small streams are fed
by rain and glaciers.
There's no shortage of water
in South Georgia.
King penguins seem to like it here.
After all, there are about 40,000 of them.
They have an unusually delayed
breeding cycle of around 14 months.
The result is that
a colony will contain year-old chicks,
as well as adults
who are still searching for a partner.
In winter, the young penguins
stay alone on land
and wait for their parents
to return after months with food.
It's summer,
the time for them to be raised and fed.
After about 14 months,
they exchange their fluffy down
for waterproof plumage.
Only then are they ready
to go fishing in the sea on their own.
While one family is still
raising its young,
an adult singleton is
on the lookout for a new partner.
Once they find each other,
the courtship begins.
It's a ritual that always leads
to the same outcome:
mating.
Not a simple business,
but definitely well worth it.
The Antarctic fur seal nearby
poses no danger.
He just has to keep an eye on his females.
Fur seals are unperturbed
by the bad weather.
They spend most of their time in water.
On land, it's all about reproduction.
There's often bitter fighting
over females and territory.
Penguins and fur seals
rarely bother each other.
Encounters are marked mainly by curiosity
or mistrust.
After careful inspection
and risk assessment,
they each go on their way.
King penguins often breed
near gentoo penguins.
Their trumpeting call is distinctive
and led to their being known
as donkey penguins in German.
They also use the short Austral summer
to rear their young.
Their nests are built of stones
and grassy padding.
They also don't mind
stealing from their neighbors.
The eggs are incubated
for around 30 days until the chicks hatch.
After that, the young typically stay
in the nest for another 30 days,
kept warm and protected by their parents.
The parent birds will have to find
over 100 kilograms of krill
before their chick is fully grown.
They take turns to forage.
One parent is always left behind
to protect their young.
Gentoo penguins only breed
in regions without snow or ice.
In South Georgia, every year,
they revisit their old breeding sites.
Good neighborliness is important,
as there's limited ice-free space
available on the island.
Everyone claims their own place.
The fur seal pups are born late November,
at the start of the Austral summer.
The baby seals often stay alone for days
while their mothers are out hunting food.
Mothers come ashore
only briefly to nurse their pups.
Fur seal pups are used
to being left on their own.
They huddle together for comfort.
Now and then,
a quarrel breaks out between adult seals,
but the worst of the fights are over,
with territories already staked out.
All in all, the cohabitation
of all these different species works well.
Fur seals, elephant seals, or penguins,
in South Georgia, there's room for all.
The reason why so many animals
are drawn to South Georgia
is its bountiful hunting grounds.
The sea here has
a wealth of nutrition resources,
making the archipelago
one of the most popular ports of call
in the South Polar Sea.
South Georgia lies at the conjunction
of the Atlantic Ocean and Antarctica.
Heading south,
the route passes by the Sandwich Islands
to the Antarctic Peninsula,
traveling ever farther into the polar sea.
The weather here is very changeable.
Cold winds from the south meet
warm air masses from the north.
This results in tremendous
low-pressure areas.
Storms and bad weather
are a foregone conclusion.
It's challenging for any expedition.
The first icebergs appear,
gigantic behemoths that have broken off
from the Antarctic ice sheet,
and are drifting north.
The sea gnaws away at them incessantly,
but the water is only a few degrees warm,
so it takes years for them to melt.
Icebergs often travel
thousands of kilometers,
driven by tides and stormy winds.
Only one-seventh of their mass sticks out
above the surface of the water.
The main section underwater
is not only much deeper,
it's also much wider,
very dangerous for shipping.
Near the Southern Antarctic Circle,
the sun hardly sets at all.
It's good for expeditions
to the Antarctic.
Volcanic islands jut out of the sea,
evidence of the massive
geological activity under the seabed,
where the oceanic plate is sliding
under the Antarctic continental plate.
The greater part of the Southern Continent
is constantly covered by a huge ice sheet.
In summer,
only 2% of the continent is free of ice.
Most of this ice-free area
is in the Antarctic Peninsula.
The nutrient-rich open water attracts
birds and other marine life to the area.
It's just one of many stops
for the Kapitan Khlebnikov.
The expeditionary ship moors
not far from the coastline.
Frequent low-pressure systems
make the local climate milder
than on the rest of the continent.
Lone gentoo penguins find ice-free spots
to go about their business.
They're usually not that sociable,
preferring close contact
only with their partner.
If both of them like the look of a place,
that will be their nesting site.
They only form colonies
during the breeding season.
This protects the chicks better
against attacks from predatory seabirds.
The lack of vegetation restricts
the choice of building materials
for their nests.
There are only small stones.
These two are just starting out,
but they have managed
to agree on a breeding spot.
Mating is just taking a little longer,
but true love will always find a way.
Others are already incubating their eggs,
while their partners waddle off
to the sea to stock up on food reserves.
On their way to the water,
they meet some excitable Adélie penguins.
Adélie penguins are the most common
penguin species in Antarctica
and can be found throughout the continent.
They're remarkably agile walkers on land.
A speed of about 2.5 kilometers per hour
is great pace for their small webbed feet.
They often walk long distances to reach
their hunting grounds in the open sea.
Distances of about 50 kilometers
are not uncommon.
To make their dangerous dive
into the water,
they usually gather at places
where the sea is rough.
Diving into the murky water together
makes it more difficult for leopard seals
that might be lurking,
waiting to grab one of them.
Like all penguins,
they appear to be quite clumsy on land.
Their streamlined bodies are
best suited to a life in the water.
They feed mostly on krill,
tiny crustaceans
that are abundant in the polar sea.
This is why they breed
in the millions here,
on the icy Southern Continent.
The Antarctic Peninsula
is still the warmest place.
In summer, temperatures can reach
above freezing,
melting the ice
and creating bizarre formations.
Sometimes a gigantic table iceberg
gets stranded near the coast.
It can be stuck for years
until it melts enough
to be able to continue its odyssey.
Only icebreakers dare
advance through the pack ice.
So for most ships,
the Antarctic Peninsula
is their last port of call.
The extreme icy conditions
make it impossible
to continue their journey
into the south polar region
or through the Weddell Sea.
Even in the summer months,
the ice prevents
any headway being made in many places.
Occasionally, the Kapitan Khlebnikov
will plow through less obstructed areas.
With the ice freezing
and melting all the time,
conditions change constantly.
Seawater freezes
at minus 1.8 degrees centigrade.
It forms a pulpy mass of ice crystals
that join together to create ice floes.
In rough seas, these floes collide
with each other and form thick plates.
This is called pancake ice.
In winter, these floes become
deeper and wider,
finally forming
a 1,000-kilometer-wide ice shield
around the whole continent.
It is only in spring,
when the ice begins to crack,
that ice-breakers can penetrate
once again as far as this.
Until then,
around 20 million square kilometers
of solid ice separates the continent
from the rest of the world.
The Kapitan Khlebnikov can deal with
pack ice several meters thick,
but traveling through
extensive sheets of ice is risky.
A special radar system helps
to assess the ice conditions.
The motto for all shipping
in the polar sea is:
the shortest way through the ice
is around the ice.
It's because a detour is still safer
than sailing straight through it.
However, this isn't always possible
in the Weddell Sea.
When the radar can no longer assess
the ice floes and open water in between,
they have to resort to a helicopter.
On reconnaissance flights, they map out
the best path through the icy labyrinth.
Even for a robust icebreaker
like the Kapitan Khlebnikov,
navigating in the Antarctic Ocean
is not an easy business.
Especially shaped bow
and massively reinforced steel cladding
protect the hull
from the sharp edges of the ice.
Powerful engines ensure that
the ship has enough propulsion and thrust.
At last, the Kapitan Khlebnikov reaches
open water again and can make headway.
The days are getting longer,
which is helpful
when plotting a course through pack ice.
The sun is low in the sky,
but this far south,
it rarely sets completely.
The Weddell Sea is famously known
as the iceberg factory.
Gigantic chunks keep breaking off
of the ice shelf and drifting north.
Along the Antarctic coastline,
there are no natural harbors
to weigh anchor.
The only option is to park in the ice.
The ship plows through the ice
at maximum speed
until it is brought to a halt
in the midst of a vast,
blindingly white ice desert
extending 2,000 kilometers to the south.
There's no environment on Earth
more hostile than this.
It would seem
as if nothing could survive here.
The Kapitan Khlebnikov can take a rest.
Frozen fast in the ice,
it merely waits until the researchers
and expedition members
are ready for the return voyage.
Despite the adverse conditions,
this place is home to the emperor penguin.
Its hunting grounds are accessed
through a hole in the ice.
These penguins have caught their fill
and are now heading back to their colony.
This could be several kilometers
from the water,
a long trek for short penguin legs,
but they have more than one method
of locomotion at their disposal.
Their smooth, oiled feathers
make it easy for them
to slide across the icy surface
beneath them.
Emperor penguin colonies are often
far away from the sea,
safe from the melting ice in spring.
The icebergs they pass are immobile,
frozen prisoners
of the white Antarctic wasteland.
They stay here
until summer breaks up the sheet ice,
freeing them from their captivity.
Wind and weather create
bizarre formations,
icy sculptures that almost look like
they were made by human hands.
It's hard to believe
that this barren landscape
could harbor any life at all,
but it's one of the biggest
nurseries in the world.
This is where emperor penguins
raise their young.
It's a risky breeding strategy,
but one that generally pays off.
In such a desolate area,
there are few enemies,
and the young can grow up
in relative safety.
Like any other chicks,
they are permanently hungry,
so their parents
must bring back loads of food.
The Antarctic summer
is the best time for this.
The days are very long,
and the more the pack ice melts,
the shorter their way
to open water becomes.
They tirelessly tramp back and forth
between their colony and the sea.
The cold sea is teeming
with fish, squid and krill,
so the adult penguins can always bring
plenty of food back to their young.
There are more than
40 colonies in the Antarctic,
and year after year,
emperor penguins return to the same ones.
In the deepest winter,
they breed by the thousands
and use the short summers
to raise their offspring.
Now there's food in abundance,
and the chicks grow fast.
There's plenty of pre-digested fish daily.
The fluffy down plumage gives the chicks
excellent protection against the cold.
The little ones are insatiable,
but begging doesn't always work.
When the supplies
in the parent's stomach have been eaten,
they have to set off again
to get more food.
The chicks often sleep
while their parents are away
for long periods,
waiting for their return.
Emperor penguins are the only animals
that reside primarily in the Antarctic.
Their bodies are perfectly adapted
to the adverse conditions
of the icy continent.
Their plumage protects them from the cold.
A base layer of warm down is covered
by a closely growing layer
of short feathers.
The top feathers are constantly oiled
by a secretion from the preen gland,
making the penguin's body
completely waterproof.
They also have a thick layer of fat,
which helps them to withstand temperatures
of up to minus 60 degrees centigrade.
Loud calls help them
to identify partners and offspring.
Emperor penguins are the largest
of the penguin species.
They can reach up to 1.3 meters in height
and weigh around 38 kilograms.
In winter, they can lose
up to 40% of their body weight.
Now, during the summer months,
they stock up again.
When both parents are away foraging,
the young penguins gather in nurseries.
They're constantly supervised
and guarded by adult birds.
Occasionally, danger can threaten
in the form of seagulls and giant petrels.
They're safer when they're in groups.
A lost chick might not be able
to find its parents again.
If that happens,
then the chick will starve.
In the safety of the group
and looked after by adults,
the chicks often go on outings.
Here and there, the walking party
is joined by others keen on a stroll.
In a few weeks, they'll grow
their proper waterproof penguin plumage.
When that happens,
they'll be able to go down to the water
and begin their lives as young adults.
The chicks receive constant care
from both parents.
It's almost impossible for a single parent
to catch enough food
to raise a young chick on its own.
When the temperature reaches
minus 20 degrees,
it gets too warm for the penguins.
This results in colonies spreading out.
The families redistribute themselves
and form scattered groups.
The fishing forays that would take months
in the winter, now take just a day or so.
Toward evening,
most penguins return to their colony.
They will spend
the short Antarctic summer nights there,
in the safety of their own family.
For emperor penguins,
this is their home and retreat.
As humans, we wonder
about the marvels of this world.
Only a few of us ever have access to it
and return to tell its tales,
tales of life and death,
friendship and family
amid the harshest conditions,
tales of Antarctica,
from the End of the World.